Guide to the Street Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Street family papers
1795-1933
MS 946
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
(4 boxes)
The major figure in these papers is Joseph Monfort Street, who was an Indian agent in Iowa in the 1820s and 1830s. Half of the collection is made up of family correspondence (1805-1931). Included is the correspondence of Joseph M. Street with his wife, Eliza Maria Posey Thornton, and his sons, and members of the Street and Posey families.Topics discussed in the letters include religion, health, national politics and slavery, particularly in reference to slaves owned by the Street family. Joseph M. Street's experiences on the frontier are documented in letters and financial records. Also in the papers are writings by Ida M. Street, William B. Street, and others on Indian affairs in the Iowa territory (1899-1901) and a day book (1795-1802) belonging to George Cheney.
Street family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. George Cheney, 1976-1982.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains papers from several generations of the family of General Joseph Montfort Street, Indian agent in Iowa in the 1820s and 1830s. Included are correspondence (arranged in chronological order), writings, legal and financial papers, genealogical papers, memorabilia, and other miscellaneous items.
The correspondence falls roughly into three groups: that of Joseph M. Street (1782-1840) and his wife, Eliza Maria (Posey) Thornton (1792-1846), with other family members, particularly Alexander Posey, from 1805 through the 1840s; that of their sons Anthony Waddy Street (1831-) and William B. Street (1819-) from the 1840s to the 1890s; and that of Ida Maria Street, daughter of William B. Street, from the 1880s through the 1930s. Throughout, the correspondence reveals the efforts of the large Street and Posey families to keep in touch despite their dispersal across the southern United States and along the frontier. While it is true that family disputes arose from time to time (see letters for 1811 Oct 28, 1816 Feb 22, 1836 May 17, 1850 Oct 29, 1851 May 30, 1852 May 23), for the most part great affection is expressed, not only between husband and wife (e.g. 1809 Dec 18), but also among members of widely separated branches of the family. Financial problems are shared and the consolation of religion is offered in times of sickness and death (1809 Jan 27, 1815 Feb 6, 1832 Sep 18, 1840 Sep 2, 1845 Apr 11). Other matters of interest include letters on local politics and corrupt elections (1808 Feb, 1831 Feb 17, 1839 Dec 4) and a campaign appeal on behalf of Abraham Lincoln (folder 30), letters about slaves owned by the Street family (1807 Oct 4, 1811 Jul 22, 1818 Feb 2, 1836 Oct 16), an indenture between Joseph M. Street and a free black woman (folder 48), certificates attesting the loyalty of William B. and Anthony Waddy Street during the Civil War (folder 48), a receipt for the sale of a slave (folder 50), and photographs of Ulysses S. Grant and of members of the Street family (folder 56).
Materials relating to Indian affairs include a letterbook kept by Joseph M. Street as Indian agent for the years 1830-1832 (the second half of the volume has been used by William B. Street as an account book); letters for the dates 1833 Jul 28, 1834 Jan 7, Jun 3-4, 1835 Dec 13, 1836 Oct 4, 1839 May, Aug 6, Dec 4, 1840 Jan 7, Feb 1, Feb 23, 1841 Apr 11, 1842 Nov 15, 1843 Feb 20; and a few other items concerned for the most part with the finances of the Indian agency (folder 47). In these materials are documented Joseph M. Street's views on the treatment of the Indians and his hopes for treaties with them, disputes among the various tribes around Prairie du Chien, and events leading up to the Black Hawk War in the 1830s. Also discussed are financial and legal difficulties in which Joseph M. Street became mired as Indian agent. Materials dealing with other aspects of Joseph M. Street's career include letters to his children describing his early travels to and life on the frontier (1836 Oct 16, 1837 Jan 25), a copy of a letter from Henry Clay (1829 Feb 16), papers, including a printed prospectus, concerning Western World (1806 Jul 31, Sep 2, Nov 8), and memorabilia such as his commission as brigadier-general (folder 48). In addition, most of the writings deal with Joseph M. Street and Indian affairs in Iowa and Wisconsin.
Information about the Street and Posey family trees can be found in folders 51 and 52, which contain notes on the two families and a copy of The Street Genealogy, published in 1895. The only item in the collection not directly related to the Street and Posey families is a daybook for 1795-1802 (folder 49) belonging to George Cheney, whose family was later connected by marriage to the Anthony Waddy Street family. It was members of this branch of the Street family, Mr. and Mrs. George Cheney, who in 1976-1977 donated the Street Family Papers to Yale University.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Families; Frontier and pioneer life -- Iowa; Husband and wife; Indians of North America; Slavery -- United States; Iowa -- History; Middle West; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Account books; Cheney, George, 1771-1829; Posey, Alexander Lawrence, 1873-1908; Street, Anthony Waddy; Street, Ida M. (Ida Maria), 1856-; Street, Joseph Montfort, 1782-1840; Street, William B., b. 1819; Thornton, Eliza Maria Posey, 1792-1846; Posey family; Street family
- Inventory, 1795-1933, undated; 20" (4 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - 1805-1809 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1811-1818 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1820-1829 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1830-1831 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1832 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1833 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1834 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1835-1836 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1837-1838 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1839 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1840-1842 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1843-1844 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1845-1848 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1849 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1850-1851 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1852 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1853 January-March (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1853 April-December (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1854 January-July (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1854 October-December (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1855 January-August (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1855 September-1859 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 1860-1873 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 1882-1892 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1893 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 1896-1899 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 1905-1920 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 1921-1931 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - undated (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    - Combined letter book and accountbook, 1830-1832, 1840-1845 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Writings
    - Hull, James: "Life of Major Genl. Thomas Posey" (ms. copy), undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Perrin, William Henry: "The Western World...," excerpted from The Pioneer Press of Kentucky, Filson Club Publications, No. 3, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Street, A.W.: notes re death of Joseph M. Street, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Street, Ida M.
      - "A Chapter of Indian History," Annals of Iowa, Vol. 3, 1899 January (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - "The Simon Cameron Indian Commission of 1838," Annals of Iowa, 1905 July-October (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - "A Century Old Chapter of Our Indian Affairs", undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - "The Yellow River School", undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Notes on Indian affairs in Iowa and Wisconsin, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Street, William. B.
      - Speeches about Joseph M. Street and Indian affairs, 1860, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - "General Joseph M. Street," Annals of Iowa, Vol. 2, 1895 July-October (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - "Life of Gen. J.M. Street", undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Wilson, George: "George, Wilson: First Territorial Adjutant of the Militia of Iowa," Annals of Iowa, Vol. 4, 1901 January (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Unknown author: "The Acquisition of Iowa Lands from the Indians"; "Indian Affairs in Iowa Territory; 1839-1843"; "Indian Affairs in Iowa Territory"; all in Annals of Iowa, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Unknown author: funeral address for Mr. Street, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Printed matter re: Silver King Coalition Mines Company (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Papers re: Indians (statements, notes, etc.), 1831-1833, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Legal papers and documents, 1818-1869, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Financial papers
    - Daybook of George Cheney, "Bought January 1st, 1796", 1795-1802 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Receipts, bills, etc., 1822-1835, 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Genealogical papers
    - The Street Genealogy, by Henry A. Street and Mary A. Street, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Notes, newspaper clippings, etc., 1855-1887, 1923, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Memorabilia, 1846-1932 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Map of Prairie du Chien, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Three leather wallets, two containing locks of hair of Street family members, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Photographs and postcards, 1863-1894, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Miscellaneous poems, undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Photographs from Middle East, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)